<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth will out a sermon preached on the 20th of June, 1683, upon the discovery of the new plot / by a presbyter of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11174399</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11174399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46517</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46517)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1432:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth will out a sermon preached on the 20th of June, 1683, upon the discovery of the new plot / by a presbyter of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Manhood and are to be sold by the booksellers of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with loss of print; p. 31 misnumbered 64.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46517:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46517:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth will out:</hi> A SERMON Preached on the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>June,</hi> 1683. upon THE DISCOVERY OF THE New PLOT.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Presbyter</hi> of the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Manhood,</hi> and are to be ſold by the Book-Sellers of <hi>London,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46517:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46517:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>PLotting <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Machevilian</hi> Wilds, and <hi>Ahitophelian</hi> Conſpiracies to ruine <hi>Kings,</hi> and involve Kingdoms and Commonwealths, in <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> hath ever been the cuſtom of ill men in all Ages of the World, who beſides a natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination they have to miſchief and rapine, which makes them delight to be fiſhing in troubled waters, are ambitious alſo, and aſpire to raiſe themſelves to wealth and grandeur upon the publick ruine; and by Sacrificing all that is Sacred, to their ambitious deſires, and their inſatiable thirſt after an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Rule, ſtrive to acquire Honour and Renown, and make their names ſwell and look big in the Rolls of Fame, by the helliſh <hi>Intricacy</hi> as well as the multiplicity and fatality of thoſe <hi>Plots</hi> whereby they vainly flatter themſelves into a confidence, that they ſhall accompliſh their accurſed Deſigns; yet no Age ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded with ſo many; nor can any Hiſtory poſſibly be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, that is able to furniſh us with a parallel of our times wherein we live, which hath abounded wonderfully, nay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to an infinite variety of thoſe kind of Contrivances; for we have found by woful experience, that almoſt nothing elſe for ſeveral years together, hath ſaluted our unhappy
<pb facs="tcp:46517:3"/>and amuſed Ears, but <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Re-Plots,</hi> real <hi>Plots</hi> and ſham-Plots. Plots to <hi>Murther</hi> our <hi>Sovereign:</hi> Change the Government, and <hi>Deſtroy the Peſtilent He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie that hath ſo long Reigned in theſe Northern Parts;</hi> and then <hi>Plots</hi> to cover thoſe <hi>Plots,</hi> and prevent their <hi>Diſcovery;</hi> or if diſcovered, then to ſerve as a ſponge to wipe out and obliterate them. All which makes it a matter of wonderful <hi>Intricacy,</hi> to know how to order and demean our ſelves, in ſuch a juncture as this is; But for thy better direction therein, I Commend thee to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious peruſal of the following Sermon, and leave thee to the Protection of <hi>Heaven;</hi> heartily wiſhing, That He whoſe <hi>Power</hi> is infinite, and whoſe <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> are both equal to his <hi>Power,</hi> would preſerve the <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> from the fatal effects of <hi>All</hi> Plots and Conſpiracies whatſoever.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46517:3"/>
            <head>TRUTH will OUT, OR, A Sermon occaſioned on the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the New-Plot.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HOSEA 10.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Their Heart is divided, now ſhall they be found faulty.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Text opened, and ſuitableneſs of it to our Times, ſhewed.</head>
               <p>NO Marvail though <hi>Iſrael</hi> be charged, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. to be an empty Vine, ſeeing their heart is devided. Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion will cauſe emptineſs of good, both in Mens Spirits, and in Church and State. The leaſt divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Heart, in any one part from another, if it be but by the prick of a Pin, is Deadly, a great gaſh in the head is Curable. There may be much difference in Mens Opinions without any great hurt, if this difference gets not to the Heart; but if once it gets there, the danger is great, <hi>Now ſhall they be found Faulty; Now ſhall they be Guilty,</hi> or as ſome Diaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Now they will Offend,</hi> as if Heart-diviſion contracted the greateſt Guilt, and by it Men were the greateſt Offenders of any. The word ſignifies alſo to Periſh, to be made Deſolate,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſo <hi>Arias Montanus, Deſolabuntur.</hi> Heart diviſion is a Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sin, by the Judgment of God upon them for it, they ſhall be convinced in their own Conſciences, and in the ſight of all Men, that they were Guilty; that by ſuch a Sin as this, they had bound themſelves over to the Juſtice of God, and thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolating Evils that came upon them, were the Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon them for thoſe Diviſions that were amongſt them. Men will not be convinced of their Sin, till Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46517:4"/>is upon them for it; and then their Conſciences will, and others ſhall ſee that God is Righteous, and they are vile and Sinful before him, even in ſuch things that before they pleaded for, or at leaſt could not be brought to own their own guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in.</p>
               <p>The Lord convince us of, and humble us for the Sinfulneſs of our Diviſions, by his Word, that Deſolating Judgments be not upon us to convince and humble us.</p>
               <p>That one Text, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. were enough alone to pierce our Hearts thorough and thorough, as touching Brotherly Love, <hi>Ye need not that I Write unto you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>for ye your ſelves are taught of God to Love one another.</hi> Oh Lord, what are we in theſe days ſuch kind of Chriſtians as theſe were? Oh that it were ſo with us, that we had no need to be wrote to, to be Preached to, concerning this. Does it appear by our Carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges one towards another, that we are Taught of God, <hi>To Love one another?</hi> But Beloved, that God may Teach us this day, attend to what ſhall be ſaid to you at this time, which I ſhall caſt into theſe five Heads:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Joyning Principles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Joyning Conſiderations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Joyning Graces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Joyning Practiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Conclude with Exhortation.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <q>Wherein we ſhall endeavour to ſet before you the Beauty and Excellency there is in the Heart, Union, and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Love of Chriſtians.</q>
               <p>But I ſhall not need to be long in theſe: For take away Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding Principles, Dividing Diſtempers, Dividing Practiſes, and be throughly convinced of the Evil of Diviſions, and one would think our Hearts ſhould of themſelves run into one another. But that I may not ſeem to leave our Wounds open, ſo that Air ſhould get into them, but endeavour the cloſing of them, and ſo the healing, I ſhall Speak ſomething to theſe five Heads.</p>
               <div n="1" type="principle">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46517:4"/>
                  <head>The Firſt Joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In the midſt of all Differences of Judgment, and Weakneſs of the Saints, it is not Impoſſible but that they may Live in Peace and Love together.</head>
                  <p>IF notwithſtanding differences from Gods mind, and many weakneſſes, there may be Peace and Love between God and his Saints: then ſurely notwithſtanding theſe things, the Saints may be at Love and Peace among themſelves. Let this be laid for a Ground, and let our Hearts be much poſſeſſed with it, we ſhall find it very helpful to our cloſing. Away with that vain conceit which hath been the great diſturber of Churches in all Ages, if Men differ in their Judgment and Practiſe in matters of Religion, though it be in things that are but the weakneſs of Godly Men, yet there muſt needs be Heart-burning and Diviſion. Let all peaceable Men deny this conſequence, let us not ſay it will be ſo, and that our words may be made good afterwards, indeed make it ſo: certainly the connection of them, is rather from the corruption of our Hearts, then from the Nature of the things.</p>
                  <p>I have Read of two Rivers in the Eaſt, <hi>Sava</hi> and <hi>Danuby,</hi> that run along in one Channel threeſcore Miles together, without any noiſe, and yet they keep themſelves diſtinct, the colour of the waters remain diſtinct all along: why ſhould we not thing it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for us to go along cloſe together in Love and Peace, though in ſome things our Judgments and Practiſes be apparently diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent one from another? I will give you who are Scholars a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to write upon your Study-doors, as needful an one in theſe times as any; it is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Opinionum varietas, &amp; Opinantium unitas non ſunt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Variety of Opinions, and unity of thoſe that hold them, may ſtand together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There hath been much ado to get us to agree: we laboured to get our Opinions into one, but they will not come together. It may be in our endeavours for agreement, we have begun at the wrong end, let us try what we can do at the other end, it may be we ſhall have better Succeſs there. Let us Labour to joyn our Hearts to engage our affections one to another: if we cannot be of one mind that we may agree, let us agree that we may be of one mind.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46517:5"/>
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> Records a Letter that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſent to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius,</hi> before he apprehended the groſſeneſs of <hi>Arius</hi> his Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, conceiving them to differ but in ſmaller things, he endeavours to Reconcile them: <hi>For that</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the things wherein you dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, concerneth not any weighty ſubſtance of our Religion, there is no reaſon why it ſhould breed at all any Diviſion in Mind, or diſcord in Doctrine; and this I ſay not to compell you in this light queſtion, of what ſort ſoever it be, altogether to condeſcend unto the ſame Sentence: and though you Diſſent amongſt your ſelves about a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſmall Importance, nevertheleſs for all that, the Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity may be ſoundly and Inviolably retained among you, and one Conſent and Fellowſhip conſerved between all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have Read of the like peaceable Diſpoſition in divers <hi>German</hi> Divines, meeting to Confer about matters of Religion in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in <hi>Marpurg.</hi> The concluſion of their Conference was this, <hi>Although we ſee we cannot hitherto fully agree about the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral preſence of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Bread and Wine, yet both parts ought to declare Chriſtian Love one to another, as far as any one can with a good Conſcience.</hi> Oh that this were the concluſion of all our Debates and Conference, wherein we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come up fully to one anothers Judgments. If we ſtay for Peace and Love till we come to the Unity of Faith in all things, we muſt ſtay for it, for ought I know, till we come to another World. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the work of the Miniſtry, till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man.</hi> The Unity of Faith, and the perfect Man, will be both together; and when they are, there will be no more need of any Miniſtry, there ſhall be no more Preaching after we are all come to this Unity: when that is done, our work is done for this World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="principle">
                  <head>The Second Joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">That ſhould never be got by Strife, that may be had by Love and Peace.</head>
                  <p>WE would all fain have our wills: now that which lies upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt upon many mens hearts, that which is the firſt thing they do, if their wills be croſſed, is preſently to ſtrive and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: but this ſhould be the laſt thing, after all other means are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: this ſhould never be made uſe of but in caſe of pure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46517:5"/>We ſhould firſt think, Is there any way in the world whereby it is poſſible we may have our deſires ſatisfied with peace, let us try this, and another way, a third, a fourth, yea, a hundred wayes, if they lye between us and the way of ſtrife, before we come to meddle with that. This rule you will find of very great uſe to order all our buſineſſes in Churches and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, of Towns, Families, yea, whatſoever concerns any of your perſons in reference to any other. The Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Rebuking the diviſions of that Church, of which they were guilty more than any, for they had many among them of raiſed parts, of Eminent gifts, and therefore puffed up more then others. Except God joyns Eminency of Grace, men of Eminent gifts joyn leſs then others, whoſe gifts are meaner. Among thoſe means he directs for union, when he ſpeaks of love: <hi>I will ſhew you,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>a more excellent way, ver.</hi> laſt; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a way of the higheſt excellency, beyond any expreſſion. The way of Love, of the engaging hearts one to another, is the only way to bring men to unity of judgment: yea, the only way when all is done, for men to have their Wills. I may give you this or the other rule to bring you to think and do the ſame thing, but that which hath an excellency in it with an <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> is the way of Love. If you could get your minds by other ways, certainly you cannot enjoy it with that ſweetneſs and comfort as you may if you have got it this way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> repented that ever he went by Sea when he might have gone by Land (it ſeems the skill of thoſe times for Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not great) but certainly there is no man living but hath cauſe to repent him that ever he got that by ſtrife and contention that he might have got by Love &amp; peace. What hinders why ſoft and gentle words may not prevaile, as well as hard and bitter language? If it may, thou provideſt ill for thine own peace and comfort, to leave this way, and betake thy ſelfe to the other. Tell me, were it a ſigne of valour in a man to draw his ſword at every Whappet that comes near him? yea at every Fly that lights upon him? Were it not folly and madneſs? Why? he may by putting forth his finger put them off from him. Thy fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cholerick ſpirit is ready to draw at every thing that thou likeſt not. This is thy folly: thou mayeſt with leſs adoe have what thou haſt a mind to. If I would put a Feather from me, I need not ſtrike violently at it, a ſoft gentle breath will do it better.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46517:6"/>Why ſhould a man labour and toyl till he ſweats again, to take up a pin? Have none of you made a great Stir in your Families about that which when the Stir is a little over you plainly fee you might have had as well with a word ſpeaking: and hath not your heart ſecretly upbraided you then? Try the next time what you can do by faire and gentle means. Why ſhould we let the ſtrength of our ſpirits run waſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Mecedon,</hi> that when one <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion</hi> railed on him, the Courtiers would have had him dealt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely with; but <hi>Philip</hi> took another courſe, he ſends for him, and ſpeak gently to him, and ſhewed great Love and reſpect to him: upon this <hi>Arcadions</hi> heart was turned, ſo as there was no man in the world that <hi>Arcadion</hi> ſpoke more Honourably of then of <hi>Philip,</hi> whereſoever he came. After a while <hi>Philip</hi> met with thoſe who would have had him to have revenged himſelf upon <hi>Arcadion,</hi> What ſay you now of <hi>Arcadion?</hi> ſayes he: How doth he now behave himſelfe? There is no man living, ſay they, ſpeaks better of you now then he. Well then, ſayes <hi>Philip,</hi> I am a better Phyſitian then you; my Phyſick hath done that which yours would never have done.</p>
                  <p>The like he reports of <hi>Fabius,</hi> who was called the Romans Target: When he heard of a ſouldier who was valiant, yet practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed with ſome others to go to ſerve the Enemy, he calls him to him, and inſtead of dealing with him in rigour, tells him he had not had recompence according to his deſert, and gives him Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable gifts, and ſo gains him to be faithfull for ever. And ſays he, <hi>As Hunters, Riders of Horſes, and ſuch as tame wilde beaſts, ſhall ſooner make them leave their ſavage and churliſh nature by gentle uſage and manning of them, then by beating and ſhackling them; ſo a governour of men ſhould rather correct by patience, gentleneſs, and clemency, then by rigour, violence, and ſeverity.</hi> None but a cruell, harſh, ſordid ſpirited man, will ſay, I had rather men ſhould feare me then Love me: God prizes moſt what he hath from us by Love.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="principle">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46517:6"/>
                  <head>The Third Joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">My good is more in the Publick then in my ſelf.</head>
                  <p>THe ſtrength, ſafety, excellency of a Cabbin in a Ship conſiſts not ſo much in the boards of the Cabbin, or the fine painting of it, as in the ſtrength and excellency of the Ship.</p>
                  <p>It is becauſe we have ſuch private ſpirits that there are ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among us: were we more publick Spirited, our conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would vaniſh. When I read of what publique ſpirits many of the Heathens were, I am aſhamed to look upon many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> hearing of the Death of his children, ſpake with an undaunted courage thus, <hi>That the gods had heard his prayer, which was, that Calamities ſhould rather befall his family, then the Common-wealth.</hi> The publikeneſs of his ſpirit made it very ſweet and Lovely: the ſtory ſays of him, he intreated them gently and Graciouſly whom he had ſubdued, ſetting forward their cauſes, even as they had been his confederates, very Friends and near Kinſmen. Publick Spirited men are men of ſweet and peaceable Spirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="principle">
                  <head>The Fourth joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">What I would have others doe to me, that I will endeavour to doe to them.</head>
                  <p>WOuld not I have others bear with me? I then will bear with them. I would have others do offices of kindneſſes to me, I will then do offices of kindneſſes to them. I would have the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of others lovely, amiable to me, mine ſhall be ſo to them. I would have others live peaceably with me, I will do ſo with them. This rule of doing to others as I would be done to, is a Law of juſtice; ſuch juſtice as keeps the peace. <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> the Roman Emperour, was much taken with this: he ſays, he Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it from the Chriſtians, if he had to deal with his common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that did wrong, he puniſhed them: but when he had to deal with men of worth and dignity, he thought it ſufficient to reprove them with this ſentence, Do as you would be done by.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 13. Sermon to the People of <hi>Antioch,</hi> makes uſe of this principle, thus, After Chriſt had ſpoken of many bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, (ſays he) he then ſays, <hi>Thoſe things you would have others doe to you, doe you to them: as if he ſhould ſay, There needs not many words, let thine owne will be thy Law: would you Receive benefits?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46517:7"/>beſtow benefits then: would you have mercy? be mercifull then: would you be commended? commend others: would you be Loved? then love. Be you the Judge your ſelf, be you the Law-giver of your owne Life. That which you hate, doe not to another. Cannot you endure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, do not you Reproach others. Cannot you endure to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers envy you? doe not you Envy others. Cannot you endure to be deceived? do not you deceive others.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="principle">
                  <head>The fifth joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">It is as great an Honour to have my will by yielding, as by overcomming.</head>
                  <p>MAny in their anger will ſay, I will be even with him. I will tell you a way how you may be above him: forgive him, by yielding, pardoning, putting up the wrong, you ſhew you have power over yourſelf, and this is a greater thing then to have power over another. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.17, 18. <hi>Now I beſeech thee, let the power of my Lord be great; pardon, I beſeech thee, the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this People, ver.</hi> 19. and by this thou mayeſt Honourably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with thy brother: hereby ſhalt thou heap coals of fire upon his head.</p>
                  <p>I have read of two famous Philoſophers falling at variance, <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> and <hi>Aeſchines, Ariſtippus</hi> comes to <hi>Aeſchines, Shall we not be friends?</hi> ſays he, <hi>Yes with all my heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aeſchines. Remember,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtippus, that though I am your elder, yet I ſought for peace. True,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aeſchines, and for this I will alwayes acknowledge you the more worthy man; for I began the Strife, and you the Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="principle">
                  <head>The Sixth Joyning Principle:</head>
                  <head type="sub">I had rather ſuffer the greateſt Evil, then do the leaſt.</head>
                  <p>IF when others wrong you, you care not what you do to Right your ſelf: This is your folly and madneſs, ſuch a one hurt me; and I will therefore miſchief my ſelf; he hath pricked me with a Pin, and I will therefore in an anger run my Knife into my Side. If in all we ſuffer we be ſure to keep from Righting our ſelves by any ways of Sin, there will not be much peace broke. Such an one is thine Enemy, and wilt thou of one Enemy make two? wilt thou alſo be an Enemy to thy ſelf, yea a greater Enemy then he or any man Living can be to thee? for all the Men in the World cannot make the Sin, Except thou wilt thy ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="principle">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:46517:7"/>
                  <head>The Seventh joyning principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">I will Labour to do good to all, but provoke none.</head>
                  <p>A Father hath not ſo much power over his child, as to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Fathers provoke not your children to wrath.</hi> Surely if a man hath not this power over his child, he hath it not over his friend, his neighbour, much leſs his ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: yet how many take delight in this, Such a thing I know will anger him, and he ſhall be ſure to have it! Oh wicked heart! doſt thou ſee that this will be a temptation to thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and wilt thou lay it before him? doſt not thou pray for thy ſelf and for him, <hi>Lord lead us not into temptation?</hi> we ſhould account it the greateſt evil to us, of all the evil of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to be any occaſion of ſin to our brother; but what an evil ſhould this be to us, to provoke our brother to ſin? if we will needs be provoking, then let the Apoſtles exhortation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Let us conſider one another to provoke unto love, and to good works:</hi> Let us not conſider one another in a way of curioſity and emulation, to envy, or find fault with one another, from whence frowardneſs, pride, hatred, diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, factions may ariſe, ſaith <hi>Hyperius</hi> upon the place; but conſider one another, ſo as we may further the good of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo as to make one another quick and active in that which is good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="principle">
                  <head>The Eighth joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Peace with all men it is good, but with God and mine own conſcience it is neceſſary.</head>
                  <p>BUt how will this joyn us one to another?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very much, both as it holdsforth the goodneſs of peace with all men, and as it carries the heart ſtrongly to the making and keeping peace with God and a mans owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This peace with God and a mans own conſcience will ſo ſweeten the heart, that it cannot but be ſweet towards every one; a man who hath ſatisfaction enough within, can eaſily bear afflictions and troubles that come without. When <hi>Saul</hi> had made great breaches between God and his ſoul, and in his owne conſcience, than he grew to be of a very froward ſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46517:8"/>towards every man; before his Apoſtaſie he was of a very meek and quiet ſpirit, but this ſowred his ſpirit, and made it grow harſh, rugged, and cruel; This is the cauſe of the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs of many men and women in their families, and with their neighbours, there are ſecret breaches between God and their own conſciences,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="principle">
                  <head>The laſt joyning Principle.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Peace is never bought too dear, but by ſin and baſeneſs.</head>
                  <p>WE uſe to ſay, We may buy Gold too dear, and ſo we may peace: but whatſoever we pay for it beſide ſin and baſeneſs, we have a good bargain, <hi>Suidas</hi> tels of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Trajan,</hi> that he would cut his own cloaths to bind up the wounds of his Souldiers. We ſhould be very pitiful to ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who are wounded to keep us whole. We ſhould bind up their wounds, though it coſt us dear; but eſpecially, our care ſhould be to bind up thoſe wounds, that by diviſions are made in Church and <hi>State:</hi> and well may we be willing to cut our cloathes to bind them up, when the evil of them is ſuch as either does or ſhould cut our hearts. But though peace be a rich merchandize, yet ſhe muſt not ſayl too far for it, not ſo far as to ſin. We read 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.13. Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> is called the Mount of corruption, becauſe of the Idolatry committed upon it. Though we are to prize Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> at a very high rate, with the Olives growing upon it, yet we muſt take heed that we make it not a Mount of corruption. We may give peace to buy truth, but we may not give truth to buy peace. We may be bold with that which is our own to purchaſe peace, but not with that which is Gods: yet we muſt not be baſe in our yielding in things natural or civil for peace ſake; that is,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we muſt not for our own private peace yield to that which is like to prove a publick diſadvantage and diſturbance. There is a notable ſtory of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperor, perceiving his Nobles and people to be offended that he was ſo ſtrongly in love with his Concubine <hi>Irene,</hi> his heart was ſo taken with her, that he grew remiſs in his regard to the Stern of the State. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be done but as <hi>Irene</hi> would have it: whatſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions there were of any good to the State, yet <hi>Irene</hi> muſt be conſulted withall before they were put in execution, and if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46517:8"/>they pleaſed not her, all was daſhed; ſo much did he dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Irene.</hi> This the Nobles and State could not bear: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at laſt ſo far conſidered the publick, as he overcame his doting affections. He brought <hi>Irene</hi> before them, and ſays, <hi>That ye may ſee how much I prize the content of my people, I ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice her to them, and ſo drew his ſword, and ſlew her with his own hands before their eyes.</hi> If according to her demerits for draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his heart away from the good of the commonwealth, ſhe had been given up to the ſword of juſtice, it might have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as well. But leſt I be thought to be too literal, give me leave to allegorize upon this <hi>Irene.</hi> Her name is a <hi>Greek</hi> name, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> it ſignifies peace: we muſt not ſo dote upon our <hi>Irene,</hi> our private peace, that the publick ſhould ſuffer for the ſake of it: This is baſeneſs: let her be ſacrificed for publick good; this is true generouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that is baſeneſs, when our yielding is through ignorance, cowardize, baſe fear, not from a principle of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and underſtanding: not ſo much out of true love to peace, as a fooliſh, ignorant, ſottiſh, ſordid ſpirit of our own: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as had we had a ſpirit of wiſdom and courage, we might have peace upon more honourable terms. Indeed many think every kind of yielding, baſeneſs, but they are for the moſt part ſuch as are not put to any great trial themſelves; but when our conſciences tell us that what we do is what the Rule allows us; it is not becauſe we would avoid trouble, but we find through Gods grace, our hearts in ſome meaſure prepared for ſuffering, if God were pleaſed to call us to it, in any thing wherein he may have glory, and the publick may be benefited. But becauſe all things duly conſidered, we ſee that God in ſuch a way ſhall have more glory, and our brethren generally more good: therefore whatſoever becomes of our particular in regard of eſteem, or other wayes, we are willing to yield, and in this we find our hearts as much cloſing with God, enjoying communion with him in all holineſs and godly fear, and in other things that go as near to us, we are able to deny our ſelves as much as ever: in this we may have comfort, that it is not baſeneſs that makes us yield, but rather the grace of God enabling us to rule over our own ſpirits. The peace that we thus purchaſe with the ſuffering much in our names, and the loſs of many comforts does not coſt us too dear.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="consideration">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46517:9"/>
                  <head>Joyning Conſiderations.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The firſt. The conſieration of the many things wherein God hath joyned us.</head>
                  <p>GOd hath joyned us together as we are men: we are not dogs, not wolves, let us not be ſo one to another: <hi>Act.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks thus to thoſe who ſtrove one with another: <hi>Sirs, ye are brethren, why do ye wrong one another?</hi> The words in the Greek are, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> men, yet are brethren. There is a conſideration in this, that ye are men: if there were no more, yet ye ſhould not ſtrive one with another, but much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering ye are brethren. If we be men, let us be humane. What is the meaning of humanity, but courteouſneſs, gentleneſs, pleaſantneſs in our carriages one towards another? But ſtill the conſideration grows higher, as we are the ſame Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of old acquaintance, in the ſame imployment, of the ſame family and kindred, but above all, joyned in ſuch a bleſſed root, the fountain of all love and peace. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4. preſents this conſideration moſt fully to us. The reaſon the Apoſtle gives, why we muſt keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, is, becauſe <hi>there is one body, and one spirit, ye are called in one hope, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and Father of all.</hi> Here you have ſeven Ones together in two or three lines. It is very much that the Spirit of God ſhould joyn ſo cloſe together ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Ones; ſurely it is to be a ſtrong argument for us to unite</p>
                  <p>Firſt, one Body. The meaneſt member, yet it is in the body. Is it comely for the body of Chriſt to be rent and torn? any reference to Chriſt might perſwade unity, but union with Chriſt as the members with the body, what heart can ſtand againſt the ſtrength of this? What can cauſe one member to tear and rend another, but madneſs?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. One Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. that one and the ſelf ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: he does not only ſay, The ſame ſpirit; but, The ſelf ſame ſpirit: and as if that not enough, he adds One to the ſelf ſame; and that yet not enough, he ſays That one, all this is in ss the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The repeating the Article hath a great elegancy in it. And is not this one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46517:9"/>Spirit the Spirit of love and meekneſs? What does a froward contentious ſpirit do in thee, who profeſſeſt thy ſelf to be a Chriſtian? What, ſays <hi>Cyprian,</hi> does the fierceneſs of Wolves, madneſs of Dogs, the deadly poyſon of Serpents, the bloudy rage of Beaſts, in a Chriſtians breaſt?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Called in one hope. Are not you heirs, joynt heirs of the ſame Kingdom, and do you contend as if one belonged to the kingdom of light, and the other to the kingdom of darkneſs?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. One Lord. You ſerve the ſame Lord and Maſter. Is it for the credit of a Maſter, that his ſervants are always wrangling and fighting one with another? Is it not a tedious thing in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that the ſervants can never agree? Mark how ill the Lord takes this, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49, 50, 51. that evil ſervant who begins to ſmite his fellow-ſervants, provokes his Lord againſt him ſo as to come upon him with ſuch ſeverity as to cut him aſunder, and to appoint his portion with the hypocrites, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he will <hi>dichotomize</hi> him, divide him in two; he by his ſmiting his fellow-ſervants makes diviſions, but his Lord will divide him. It may be he pretends that his fellow-ſervants do not do their duty as they ought; as if he were more careful of the honour of his Lord, then others who are of a different way from him.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. One Faith. What though we agree not together in ſome things of leſſer moment, yet we agree in one faith. Why ſhould we not then keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace? The agreement in the faith one would think ſhould ſwallow up all other diſagreements. We ſhould rather bleſs God for keeping men ſound in the faith, then contend with them for leſſer miſtakes. When the Phariſees, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.9. underſtood that <hi>Paul</hi> agreed with them in that great doctrine of the Reſurrection, they preſently overlook his other differences, ſaying, <hi>We find no evil in this man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Epiſtle to our Countreymen at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> fled for their lives in witneſs to the truth, yet miſerably jarring and contending one againſt another there, to the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of all the Churches of God in thoſe Parts, begins his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle thus, <hi>This doth grievouſly torment me; it is extremely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd that diſſentions ſhould ariſe among brethren, Exiles, fled from their countrey for the ſame faith, and for that cauſe which alone
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46517:10"/>in this your ſcattering, ought to be to you as a holy band, to keep you fast bound together.</hi> Their contentions were about Church-worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. One Baptiſm. We are baptized into Chriſts death, and is not that to ſhew that we ſhould be dead to all thoſe things in the world that cauſe ſtrife and contention among men? Our Baptiſm is our badg, our livery, it furthers ſomewhat the unity of ſervants that they wear all one livery.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. One God. Though there be three Perſons in the Divine Nature, and every Perſon is God, yet there is but one God; here is an union infinitly beyond all unions that any creature can be capable of; themyſtery of this union is revealed to us, to make us in love with union. Our intereſt in this one God is ſuch a conjunction, as nothing can be more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.17. looked upon this, as having very great power in it to make up all breaches, to heal all old grudges. After their Father was dead, their conſciences miſgave them for what they had done to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid old matters would break forth, and that <hi>Joſeph</hi> would turn their enemy; now how do they ſeek to unite <hi>Joſephs</hi> heart to them? <hi>We pray thee,</hi> ſay they, <hi>forgive the treſpaſs of the ſervants of the God of thy Father;</hi> and the Text ſays, <hi>Joſeph wept when they ſpake unto him.</hi> Oh this was a heart-breaking ſpeech to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> The ſervants of the God of my Father; Shall my heart ever be eſtranged from the ſervants of the God of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? The Lord forbid. Their offence indeed was great, but their God is my God, and he was my Fathers God: this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had more in it to draw <hi>Joſephs</hi> heart to them, then if they had ſaid, We are your brethren, we came from the ſame loyns you did: True, that is ſomething, but the ſervants of the God of thy Father is much more. Let us look upon all the godly though thy have many weakneſſes, though they have not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried themſelves towards us as they ought, yet they are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, yea the children of our God, and of our fathers God; let this draw our hearts to them. If they be one with us, in their intereſt in one God, let them be one with us in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our heart, to love them, delight in them, and rejoyce in communion with them.</p>
                  <p>One God and Father, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Have we not all one Father? hath not one God Created us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46517:10"/>Is it ſeemly that one mans children ſhould be always conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, quarrelling, and miſchieving on another? do you think this is pleaſing to your Father? It follows in that of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> You have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in your Father to ſatisfie your ſouls for ever, whatſoever you want other wayes; he is above all; he that is ſo glorious and bleſſed, infinitly above all things, hath put honour enough upon you, that he is your Father; why will you contend and quarrell about trifles? He hath abſolute authority to diſpoſe of all things as he pleaſeth; let not the different adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his, to ſome in one kind, to ſome in another, be matter for you to contend about. <hi>And he worketh in all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You will ſay, If indeed we could ſee God in ſuch, if we could ſee grace and holineſs in them, our hearts would cloſe with them, but we ſee not this.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Take heed thou doſt not reject any from being thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whom Jeſus Chriſt at the great day will own for his, and God the Father will call Child.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Suppoſe thou canſt not be ſatisfied in their godlineſs, yet the gifts of the Spirit of God that are in them, ſhould cauſe ſome kind of cloſing; common gifts are of a middle nature, between nature and grace, as the ſpirits of men are neither of the ſame nature with the ſoul, nor of the body, but between both, and ſerve to unite the ſoul and body together, which otherwiſe are of natures very different. The common gifts that men who are not yet ſanctified have, may and ſhould cauſe ſome union between the godly and them while they live in this world, ſo far as to be uſeful one to another in what God hath given them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="consideration">
                  <head>The ſecond joyning Conſideration.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Let us conſider how far we can agree.</head>
                  <p>WE differ thus and thus, but what do we agree in? do we not agree in things enough, wherein we may all the dayes of our lives ſpend all the ſtrength we have in glorifying God together? Many men are of ſuch ſpirits, as they love to be altogether buſied about their brethrens differences; their diſcourſe, their pens, and all their wayes are about theſe, and that not to heal them, but rather to widen them. You ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46517:11"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hear them ſpeak of, or meddle with their agreements; their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ength is not bent to heighten and ſtrengthen them: if at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time they do take notice of their agreements, it is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke advantage of them, to render their diſagreements the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore odious, or to ſtrengthen themſelves in what they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ffer from them; they deſire to get in men, and to get from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em, only to ſerve their own turns upon them, this is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vil ſpirit. No marvel therefore though ſome be ſo loth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſcover to them how near they can come to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us of <hi>Apelles,</hi> that drawing the face of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the King who had but one eye, that he might hide this defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, he deviſed to paint him turning his viſage a little away, ſo he ſhewed but the one ſide of his face: and from him, ſays <hi>Pliny,</hi> came the invention firſt of concealing the defects and blemiſhes of the Viſage. But the Painters of our time are quite in another way, if there be any deformity, or defect on any ſide, they will be ſure to paint that ſide in all the lineaments of it, that muſt be ſet forth fully to the View of all men; yea if it may be made to look more ugly and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous then it is, all the skill they have ſhall be improved to do it. But my Beloved, this ought not to be: God doth not ſo with us: he takes notice of the good of his Children, but conceals their evil. There was but one good word in <hi>Sarahs</hi> ſpeech to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.12. ſhe called him Lord, the ſpeech otherwiſe was a ſpeech of unbelief, yet the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking afterwards of her, in reference to that ſpeech 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. conceals all the evil, and mentions only that reverend title ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> gave to her Husband, commending her for it. Thus ſhould we do; had we peacable hearts, thus we would do: All the good of our Brethren we would improve to the uttermoſt, and what is evil, ſo far as with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience we might (and no farther) we would conceal.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When I ſhall ſee this temper in mens Spirits, I ſhall hope there will be peace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="consideration">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46517:11"/>
                  <head>The third joyning Conſideration:</head>
                  <head type="sub">Let us conſider of mans Temper, Spirits, Temptations, Education, Years, Gifts.</head>
                  <p>THere muſt be a due conſideration of all theſe, and we muſt indulge ſomething to them all. This would allay much ſtrife: as we read <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.23. <hi>Every thing that may abide the fire, ye ſhall make go thorough the fire, and all that abideth not the fire ye ſhall make go thorough the water.</hi> We muſt deal with every man according to his temper. Some men are by their complexions of a more harſh and rugged temper then others. Conſider what is the beſt way of dealing with ſuch: in the main they are faithful and uſeful; they will joyn with you there, and ſpend their lives for you: if the harſhneſs of their natures cauſe ſome excreſcencies, unpleaſing carriages, conſider their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, though no evil in them is to be juſtified, yet deal ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly with them, indulge them what lawfully you may. Some mens ſpirits, though upright to God and you, yet they have a fervor in them that is not qualified with that wiſdom, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, humility, as they ought, do not preſently take theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages againſt them, that they in their heat may perhaps give you; do not fly upon them as if thoſe unjuſtifiable expreſſions that come from them, came from a ſpirit of malignity: <hi>You know the man and the manner of his communication; paſs by weakneſſes, accept of uprightneſs.</hi> Some mens temptations are very ſtrong; it may be their hearts are preſſed with diſappointments, it may be they are pricked with the want of many comforts you have, they have family-temptations, and perſonal temptations that you are free from: you do not know what you might do if you were under the like temptations. Bleſs God that you are delivered from them; but do not add to your brethrens afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by taking advantages againſt them, but according to the rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>If a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted. Bear ye one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi> Conſider their education, ſome all their days have lived in wicked families, they never were acquainted with the ſociety
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46517:12"/>of the Saints, with that way of Godlineſs that have the moſt ſtrictneſs and power in it. You muſt not deal with them for all things you ſee amiſs in them, in the ſame way you would deal with ſuch who have had godly education, who have had acquaintance with the moſt ſtrict and powerful wayes of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, but now manifeſt a ſpirit againſt them.</p>
                  <p>Conſider mens years: old age looks for reſpect, and juſtly; eſpecially ſuch as have gone thorough the brunt, and ſuffered much for your good: though ſome infirmities ſhould break forth that are incident to old age, we muſt cover and paſs by what we can, not forgetting that reverent reſpect that is due to the heary head found in the way of godlineſs. Conſider mens gifts: it may be they are not able to riſe to your height, to underſtand what you do; thank God for your ſtrength, but be not angry with your brother becauſe he is weaker. This was one of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for peace that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in that forementioned Letter of his to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius,</hi> uſed; we are not in all things like minded, neither have we all the ſame nature and gift in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="consideration">
                  <head>The fourth joyning Conſideration.</head>
                  <head type="sub">What we get by contention will never quit coſt.</head>
                  <p>A Merchant thinks it an ill venture, if when he caſts up his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts he finds the charge of his voyage riſes to more then his incomes. If thou haſt ſo much command of thy ſpirit, if thou canſt ſo far overcome thy paſſions as to get a time in cool blood to caſt up thy accounts truely, what good thou had done, or what thou haſt got by ſuch and ſuch contentions; and on the other ſide caſt up what the hurt thou haſt done, what ſin hath been committed, what evil hath got into thy ſpirit, I fear you will have little cauſe to boaſt of, or rejoyce in your gains. <hi>To be freed from that expence that comes in by ſtrife, is not a little gain,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> In ſtrife you will find there is a very, great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of time, of gifts, and parts. Many men in regard of the good gifts God hath given them, might have proved ſhining Lights in the Church, but by reaſon of their contentious ſpirits, they prove no other then ſmoaking firebrands. It may be by all the ſtir you keep you ſhall never get your mind; if you do, it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46517:12"/>will not quit coſt; the charge you have been at for it, comes to much more then it is worth. God deliver me from having my mind at ſuch a dear rate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="consideration">
                  <head>The fifth. Conſider how the heart of God is ſet upon making peace with us, and what it coſt him.</head>
                  <p>GOd was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf: this work hath taken up the thoughts, counſels, heart of God from all eternity above any thing that ever he did: this is the chief maſter-piece of all the workers of God. There is more of the glory of God in this, then in all that God hath done. This is and ſhall be the object of the admiration of Angels and Saints, the matter of their praiſes to all eternity. The heart of God was ſo in this, that he was reſolved to have it whatſoever it coſt him; it coſt the deareſt that ever any thing in this world did; yea the price of it was more then ten thouſand worlds are worth: it was no leſs then the blood of the Son of God, of him who is the ſecond perſon in Trinity, God bleſſed for evermore. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. <hi>In whom we have redemption through his blood who is the image of the inviſible God, the firſt born of every creature: by him were all things created, he is before all things: by him all things conſiſt, in him all fulneſs dwells: and having made peace through the blood of his Croſs, ver.</hi> 20. What God hath done for peace with us, calls aloud to us to prize peace one with another. It is the Apoſtles argument, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>He laid down his life for us, we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.</hi> It coſt his life to make our peace with God. We ſhould be willing to do any thing we are able, even to the hazard of our lives, to make peace among the Saints. Chriſt laid down his life even for this peace alſo, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>For he is our peace who hath made both one, and hath broke down the middle wall of partition between us, having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, to make in himſelf of twain one new man, ſo making peace, and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the Croſs.</hi> Chriſt reconciles both unto God: but how? it is in one body. Lay this Conſideration warm at your hearts, and it will comfort your hearts, and ſo preſerve and encreaſe peaceable diſpoſitions in you towards one another.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="consideration">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46517:13"/>
                  <head>The Sixth. Conſider the preſence of God and of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>OUr God, our Father, our Maſter, our Saviour, ſtands by looking on us. It is a moſt excellent paſſage that I find in an Epiſtle of <hi>Luther</hi> to the Miniſters of <hi>Norimberg.</hi> There were great diviſions amongſt them: he writes to them that he might pacifie their ſpirits one towards another. <hi>Suppoſe</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>you ſaw Jeſus Chriſt ſtanding before you, and by his very eyes ſpeaking thus unto your hearts, What do you, O my dear children, whom I have redeemed with my blood, whom I have begotten again by my Word, to that end that you might love one another? Know that this is the note of my Diſciples. Leave this buſineſs, ye wholly caſt it upon me, Ile look to it, there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that the Church ſhould ſuffer by this, though it ſhould be ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yea though it ſhould dye, but there is a great deal of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if you diſſent amongſt your ſelves, if you bite one another: Do not thus ſadden my ſpirit, do not thus ſpoile the holy Angels of their joy in heaven; am not I more to you then all matters that are between you? then all your affections? then all your offences? What? can any words of a brother, can any unjuſt trouble penetrate your hearts, ſtick ſo faſt in you as my wounds, as my blood, as all that I am to you, your Saviour Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Oh that we had ſuch real apprehenſions of Chriſt looking upon us, ſpeaking to us!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="consideration">
                  <head>The Seventh. Conſider what account we can give to Jeſus Chriſt of all our Diviſions.</head>
                  <p>WHen Chriſt ſhall come, will you ſtand before him with ſcratched faces, with black and blew eyes? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>The Lord make you to increaſe and abound in love one towards another, and towards all men:</hi> To what end? <hi>To the end,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>he may eſtabliſh your hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable in holineſs before God, even our Father, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with all his Saints.</hi> It will be a ſad thing to be found in our diviſions, at the coming of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46517:13"/>Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.50. the coming of Chriſt is mentioned as a terror to thoſe who ſhall but <hi>begin to ſmite their fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi> We may wrangle and ſtand out one againſt another in our contentions now; but it will not be ſo eaſie to anſwer Jeſus Chriſt, as it is to anſwer one another. In the Name of Jeſus Chriſt I now ſpeak unto you, yea as from him charge you, let no inconſiderable reaſon move you to contend with, diſſent or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from your brethren, but live together in Love &amp; Unity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="consideration">
                  <head>The Eighth. Let us conſider our mortality.</head>
                  <p>IT is but a little time we have to live; ſhall the greater part of it, nay why ſhould any part of it be raveld out with cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and quarrels? I have read of <hi>Pompey,</hi> that upon a time paſſing over divers hills, where there lived many people in caves, but their order was that the man lived in one cave and the wiſe in another; he asking the reaſon, they ſaid, In thoſe parts they live not long, therefore they deſired that the little time they did live, they might have peace and quiet, which they had found by experience they could not have, if man and wife live conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together. Though the means they uſed for their quiet was ſordid, yet the good uſe they made of the ſhortneſs of their lives was commendable. <hi>Vilgil</hi> ſayes, if ſwarms of Bees meet in the air, they will ſometimes fight as it were in a ſet battel with great violence; but if you caſt but a little duſt upon them, they will all be preſently quiet. Sprinkle upon your hearts the meditations of death, that within a while this fleſh of yours will be turned to duſt, this will quiet you.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="consideration">
                  <head>The Ninth. Conſider the life of heaven.</head>
                  <p>THere is and will be perfect agreement there. We are here as Bees, flying up and down from flower to flower all day, but at night they come all into the ſame Hive; That is a place where <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> will well agree: Shall not we whom God from all eternity hath ordained to live co-heirs in heaven, to joyn together in praiſes there, agree together here on earth?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:46517:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Joyning graces.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="grace">
                  <head>1. <hi>Wiſdom.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe deepeſt ſeas are the moſt calm, ſo men of the deepeſt judgments are moſt quiet. <hi>A man of underſtanding is of an excellent ſpirit, Prov.</hi> 17.27. or thus, <hi>is of a cool ſpirit,</hi> for ſo the word ſignifies; his ſpirit is not heat with paſſion, there is a cool dew of examination and deliberation upon his ſpirit, he weighs the circumſtances, conſequences, and iſſues of things; he orders and diſpoſes of things ſo, as jarrs, contradictions and oppoſitions are prevented. <hi>The wiſdom that is from above is pure, peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, James</hi> 3.17. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Wiſdom have a majeſty in them, and will force reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Let paſſion reverence the preſence of Reaſon, ſayes <hi>Baſil,</hi> as children doing things unſeemly are afraid of the preſence of men of worth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="grace">
                  <head>2. <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. THis unites us to Chriſt and God, and in them to one another.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Faith commits all cauſes, all fears, injuries to God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Faith lays hold upon, and improves thoſe gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that God hath made to his Churches for union. Faith ſues out the Bond.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Faith is able to deſcry the iſſue of troubles and afflictions; Though Senſe ſayes, It will not be, Reaſon, It cannot be, yet Faith gets above, and ſayes, It ſhall be, I deſcry land: and thus it quits all in the ſoul; all being quiet there, the turbulent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are in our ſpirits one towards another are ſoon quieted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="grace">
                  <head>3. <hi>Humility.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>COloſſ. 3.12. <hi>Put on as the elect of God, bowels of mercies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind.</hi> Epheſ. 4.2. <hi>With all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and meekneſs, and long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love, endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> Philip. 2.3. <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain glory, but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem others better then himſelf.</hi> We may ſay of Humility, as <hi>Tertullus, Acts</hi> 24. ſaid
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46517:14"/>of <hi>Felix, By thee we enjoy great quietneſs.</hi> An humble heart looks upon every truth of God as infinitely above it ſelf, therefore it is willing to receive it from any; a child may lead it, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.6. One <hi>Baldaſſar,</hi> a German Divine, writing to <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> hath this notable expreſſion, <hi>Let the Word of the Lord come, let it come, and we will put under ſix hundred necks if we had them.</hi> Such a diſpoſition as this would make much for peace. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 32.18, 19. we have a promiſe, that the people of God ſhould dwell in <hi>a peaceable habitation, and in quiet reſting places, and the City ſhall be low, in a low place.</hi> When the heart lyes loweſt, it is quieteſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="grace">
                  <head>4. <hi>Self-denyal.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe joynts in the body cannot joyn, but one part muſt be hollow, and give way to the other. Condeſcention of one to another is a principal thing in friendſhip. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt emptying himſelf, and making himſelf to be of no reputation, is ſet before us as an argument for our union, that therefore we ſhould <hi>do nothing through ſtrife, be like min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, having the ſame love, and be of one accord, and one mind.</hi> It is indifferent to a heart emptyed of Self, whether it conquers, or be conquered, ſo Truth may triumph. In other conflicts the Conquerour hath the honour, and the conquered is diſgraced; but in the conflict for truth, both conquered and conquerour are honourable; the mercy is the greater to him that is conquered, but he muſt have a ſelf-denying heart to make him think ſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="grace">
                  <head>5. <hi>Patience.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Olive, the Emblem of Peace, will continue green, though overflown by the waters for a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. After <hi>Noah</hi> had been ſo long in the Ark, the Dove brought an Olive leaf in her mouth to him. It may be an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of Patience as well as Peace. Patience and Peaceableneſs are near akin. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.2, 3. Long-ſuffering is amongſt the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where the unity of the ſpirit is to be kept in the bond of peace.</p>
                  <p>There is a notable ſtory I find in the lives of the German Divines: One <hi>Vitus Theodorus</hi> a Divine, ſends to adviſe with <hi>Melancthon</hi> what he ſhould do when <hi>Oſiander</hi> preached againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46517:15"/>him; <hi>Melancthon</hi> writes to him, and beſeeches him for the love of God, yea charges him, that he ſhould not anſwer <hi>Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> again, but that he ſhould hold his peace, and behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as if he heard nothing. <hi>Vitus Theodorus</hi> writes back again, This was very hard, yet he would obey. Let not men be too haſty to oppoſe oppoſitions, but let them go on patiently in a conſtant way, reſolving to bear what they meet with, and God at length will make their righteouſneſs break forth as the light. Confute evil reports by thy life. <hi>He that knows not to bear calumnies, reproaches, injuries, he knows not how to live,</hi> ſaies <hi>Chytraeus,</hi> another German Divine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="grace">
                  <head>6. <hi>Joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ROm. 14.17. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is righteouſneſs, peace, joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> This grace in the heart puts a grace upon all a mans converſation; it makes it lovely and amiable. The beams of the Sun ſhining upon the fire will put it out; The beams of this ſpiritual Joy will put out the fire of our paſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="grace">
                  <head>7. <hi>Meekneſs, Gentleneſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MIlk quenches Wild-fire, Oyle (ſays <hi>Luther</hi>) quenches Lime, which water ſets on fire. Oppoſition will heat, will fire men, when meekneſs and gentleneſs will ſtill and quench all. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſays, <hi>Sweetneſs in ſpeech and carriage is that which ſeaſons friendſhip; ſeverity in every thing and ſadneſs muſt not be among friends in their converſe; ſuch a kind of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage may have a ſeeming gravity, but friendſhip muſt have a remiſneſs, it muſt be more free and ſweet, diſpoſed to all mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and eaſineſs,</hi> Epheſ. 4.2, 3. Meekneſs comes in as a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al grace for peace and unity, ſo <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="grace">
                  <head>8. <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat is the ſpecial uniting grace; Faith indeed hath the preheminence in our union with Chriſt our head, but Love is the Grace that Unites the Members. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13. the Apoſtle ſhews many of his Fruits of this Grace, all tending to Union and Peace; <hi>It ſuffers long, it envies not, it is not puffed up, it behaves not it ſelf unſeemly, it ſeeketh not her own, it is not eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, thinketh no evil, beareth all things, believeth all things,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46517:15"/>hopeth all things, endureth all things; Bearing</hi> all things, and <hi>Endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> all things ſeem to be the ſame, therefore ſome would have it, it <hi>covereth</hi> all things, for ſo the word alſo ſignifies; but there is a greater elegancy in it in the Tranſlation, <hi>Beareth all things,</hi> it is like the croſs main Beam in a Houſe, ſupporting the whole Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and were it not for ſome who have the love of God and his truth, and the good of the publick, enabling them to undergo what they do, all things in Church and State would be ready to fall into confuſion, to be nothing but a heap of Rubbiſh, but this Love ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to bear all things: But if they have no encouragement, but ſee that thô they hazard themſelves never ſo much, be of never ſo great uſe, do the greateſt Services that can be expected from men, yet when mens turns are ſerved, they are little regarded, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed and narrowly watched. 4. Spy out any thing that may have ſome ſhew of excepting againſt them, and left to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as well as they can, when they might juſtly expect a greater reward of their Services, yet are diſappointed, their hearts are griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but yet becauſe they are acted by a principle of Love to God, his cauſe, the publick, they therefore ſtill hold out, go on in their way, labour to be as inſtrumental as they can for good, commit themſelves and all their endeavours to God, expecting encouragement from him, and ſo they endure all things; ſuch men are worth their weight in gold; here is a heart that hath much of the Spirit of God in it: <hi>God is love, and he that dwelleth in love, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in God, and God in him:</hi> No marvel though theſe men act ſo ſwiftly in their way; no marvel though their motion in publique ſervice be ſo ſpeedy, for their Charet is like that Charet of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> Cant. 3.10. <hi>The middle thereof is paved with love, and this is for the daughters of Jeruſalem:</hi> Now the love of God be for ever with theſe his ſervants, the bleſſing of the Almighty, and all his Saints, be with them, upon them, in them and theirs for ever.</p>
                  <p>Theſe with other uniting graces that might be mentioned, are the graces that God expects ſhould be in a ſpecial manner acted in theſe times; and this is in a holy manner <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to ſerve the time, as ſome Copies have it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. This is the moſt ſuitable work for the times wherein we live. What is more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for divided times than uniting graces? and that union that comes from the acting of theſe graces, is a ſpiritual, holy, truly Chriſtian union, a raiſed union to a far higher pitch than any natural excellencies can raiſe unto. It is an excellent ſaying
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46517:16"/>of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, If the ſpiritual man be in us, our huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is fraternity.</hi> What then is our fraternity? it is raiſed to that which hath no name to expreſs it: The union of the Saints in heaven is beyond the union of fraternity; this which is of grace is of the ſame nature.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Joyning Practices.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="practice">
                  <head>The firſt, the practice of the Tongue. Gentle Language.</head>
                  <p>A <hi>Soft anſwer turneth away wrath,</hi> Prov. 15.1. In your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes let your arguments be as hard as you will, but let your words be ſoft. Soft words and hard arguments make a good diſpute: Gentle language gains much upon the hearts of men, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.2. <hi>Hear me my Brethren, and my People,</hi> ſayes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi> This was better, and tended more to union between King and People, than the ruggid churliſh anſwer of <hi>Rehoboam, My Father made your yoak heavy, and I will add to your yoak:</hi> But what came on it? Ten Tribes were rent from him; as good a man as he could ſay, <hi>Hear me my Brethren and my People:</hi> Good words are as cheap as bad, gentle courteous language is as eaſie as rough and bitter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.21. <hi>Napthali</hi> is ſaid to <hi>give goodly words, ſayings of goodlineſs or fairneſs;</hi> ſo the Hebrew hath it, that is, fair, pleaſing words; this Tribe were fair ſpoken men: Now compare this with <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.23. There <hi>Napthali</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>ſatisfied with favour, and full with the bleſſing of the Lord:</hi> Fair, courteous language hath an acceptation among men, and the bleſſing of God is with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="practice">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond joyning Practice. Be ingenuous.</hi> 1. <hi>Do not lye at the catch to take advantages.</hi> 2. <hi>Make the beſt interpretation of things you can.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF God ſhould catch advantages againſt us, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us? This is moſt unſeemly, when men are ſeeking to find out truth, if then they ſhall piddle about words, catch at phraſes, get hold of Expreſſions, and ſeek to make their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46517:16"/>out of them; and in this ſhall be the greateſt ſtrength of their anſwer, though this may have a ſpecious ſhew before men, who are willing to receive any thing which makes againſt what they would have cruſhed, yet this will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> abide before the throne of Chriſt. We read <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. Chriſt had a great diſpute with the Devil, in which he had him at great advantage in his quotation of a Scripture, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge concerning thee, and in their hands they ſhall bear thee up, leſt at any time thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> This was quoted out of the 91. <hi>Pſal. ver.</hi> 11. there it is, <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee in all thy wayes.</hi> Yet Chriſt did not catch this advantage, he did not ſo much as upbraid him for leaving out that paſſage, which he might juſtly have done, but he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the thing. Yea Chriſt might have taken a further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt the Devil, for the words following in the Pſalm are a Propheſie of Chriſt deſtroying the power of the Devil; <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and Adder, the young Lyon and the Dragon ſhalt thou trample under thy feet.</hi> Chriſt did not take the advantage of this neither, and upbraid him with it, he had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough againſt him in the thing it ſelf he brought. It is a ſign that men have leſs advantage in the matter, when they ſeek ſo much to catch at all the advantages they can in the manner of the expreſſions of thoſe whom they oppoſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Make the beſt interpretation of things you can, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Love thinks no evil.</hi> It may be if you meet with a man in the ſtreets, if he ſtayes not to talk with you, if he takes not ſpecial notice of you, you preſently think it is his pride, his ſleighting, diſregarding you, this is the worſt interpretation that can be. Why? is it not poſſible that it may be thorough multitude of buſineſs in his head that you know not of? May it not be that his eyes and thoughts were another way? he did not take notice of your paſſing by him; is it not thus often with your ſelf in reſpect of others? Again, perhaps ſuch a man you find not in his behaviour towards you when you are with him, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſmilingly upon you, carrying himſelf in that familiar affable way as you expected; you preſently think and ſay, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is his pride and ſurlineſs, whereas it may be it is becauſe his head is fuller than yours, which may afterwards be for your good, if you would be but patient a while; it may be it is from ſome trouble of his Spirit at that time; it may be it is from the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46517:17"/>temper of his body, his conſtitution, or ſome weakneſs in it at that time; if ſuch a fair Interpretation may be made, why ſhould not an ingenuous candid ſpirit mke it? This very exception I find was taken againſt <hi>Baſilius Magnus,</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in one of his Orations, in which he highly commends <hi>Baſil,</hi> anſwers it, and juſtifies him; It is hard to keep unity, love, and peace with men who are of exceptious carping diſpoſitions; if God were ſtrict to mark what we do amiſs, what would become of us? God is ſtrict to mark what good there is in his Saints? if there be any little good in the midſt of much imperfection, Gods way is to paſs by the imperfection, and take notice of the good; but our way is often, if there be a little bad, though but through a very pardonable miſtake, in the midſt of much good, to paſs by all the good, and to ſeize upon the miſtake, to make it the ſeed of contention, to brood over it, and ſo beget the brats of Contention from it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="practice">
                  <head>The third joyning prastice: If you will needs be ſtriving: ſtrive who ſhall do one another moſt good, who ſhall engage one another in the most and greatest offices of love.</head>
                  <p>THis is a good combat; ſuch ſtriving as this is, God and his bleſſed Angels look upon, and take much delight in.</p>
                  <p>I find a notable ſtory in the life of <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> which may put on and encourage Chriſtians in ſuch a combat as this: There was a great King in <hi>India,</hi> his name was <hi>Taxiles,</hi> who on a time came to ſalute <hi>Alexander,</hi> and ſaid unto him, <hi>What ſhould we need to fight and make Wars one with another, if thou comest not to take away our water and our neceſſary commodity to live by, for which things men of judgment must needs fight? as for other goods, If I be richer than thee, I am ready to give thee of mine; and if I have leſs, I will not think ſcorn to thank thee, if thou wilt give me ſome of thine. Alexander</hi> being pleaſed to hear him ſpeak thus wiſely, embraced him, and ſaid unto him, <hi>Thinkest thou that this meeting of ours can be without fight, for all theſe goodly fair words? No, no, thou hast won nothing by them, for I will fight and contend with thee in honesty and courteſie, becauſe thou ſhalt not exceed me in bounty and liberality.</hi> So <hi>Alexander</hi> took divers gifts of him, but gave more to him.</p>
                  <p>Oh that our contentions were turned into ſuch contentions as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46517:17"/>theſe are! Let us rejoyce in any opportunity of doing any Office of love to thoſe we differ from, yea to thoſe who have wronged us. It was wont to be ſaid of Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> If you would be ſure to have <hi>Cranmer</hi> do you a good turn, you muſt do him ſome ill one; for though he loved to do good to all, yet eſpecially he would watch for opportunities to do good to ſuch as had wronged him. Had we but a few leading men of ſuch ſpirits among us, how great a bleſſing of Peace might we yet enjoy!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="practice">
                  <head>Laſtly, pray much.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PLiny</hi> ſayes of the Pearles they call Unions, though they be engendred in the Sea, yet they participate more of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens than of the Sea. Certainly this precious Union, though it be amongſt men, yet it hath its luſtre and beauty, yea its very being from the Heavens. You muſt look up to Heaven there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for Peace, for the preſervation, increaſe, luſtre, beauty of it if you would have it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Job</hi> 25.2. <hi>God maketh peace in his high places, the Lord can make peace between high and low.</hi> Let us carry mens rugged, crooked, perverſe hearts to God in Prayer, who is the great joyner of hearts; it is he that <hi>makes men to be of one mind in a houſe, he maketh the wars to ceaſe.</hi> Pſal. 122.6. <hi>Pray for the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem. In your prayers for the Church this muſt be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as a ſpecial bleſſing. If praying prevail not, fighting will not. Thoſe are the moſt peaceable men in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that pray moſt for the peace of them; God hath more prayers for the peace of this Church and State upon the file, of theirs whom ſome of you, beloved, account hinderers of it, than of yours. You complain much for want of peace, you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh much againſt thoſe whom you are pleaſed to mark out as hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of the peace, but do you pray as much? You have theſe means preſented unto you for the furtherance of peace; what other you may meet with any way, make uſe of. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Lord of peace give you peace alwaies by all means.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that all may be the better improved, let the exhortation of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.11. ſink into you, <hi>Study to be quiet,</hi> the words are, <hi>Love the honour of being quiet:</hi> There is great excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:46517:18"/>
               <head>CAP. V. <hi>Exhortation to peaceable and brotherly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, ſhewing the excellency of it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND now, my brethren, as the Eunuch ſaid to <hi>Philip</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Baptiſm, <hi>Here is water, what lets but I may be baptized,</hi> I ſhall ſay concerning our uniting in peace and love one with another. Here are <hi>Joining Principles, Joining Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, Joining Graces, Joining Practices;</hi> what now lets, but that we may join in love and peace one with another? ſurely nothing can let but extream corrupt, perverſe hearts of our own.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is mighty earneſt in his deſires, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations for this: 1 Cor. 1.10. <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joined together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment. The</hi> word tranſlated <hi>perfectly joined,</hi> ſignifies ſuch a joining, as when a bone is out of joint, is perfectly ſet right again.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.1. <hi>If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind, let nothing be done through ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle pours forth his Soul in this exhortation, it is a heart-breaking exhortation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther,</hi> though a man of a ſtirring, hot ſpirit, yet writing to the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Stratsburg,</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>I pray you be perſwaded, that I ſhall alwaies be as deſirous to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace concord, as I am deſirous to have the Lord Jeſus to be propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I find alſo in a Letter that <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> writes to a godly Miniſter, a very high expreſſion of that high eſteem he had of and earneſt deſires after the curing of diviſions: <hi>Who would not</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>purchaſe with his life, the removing that infinite ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal that comes by Diſſention?</hi> Oh that there were ſuch hearts in us! Chriſt expects it from us all, but eſpecially from his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for they are his Ambaſſadors for peace, to beſeech men in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46517:18"/>his ſtead to be reconciled to God; reconciliation with God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile us one to another: <hi>If God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one another,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.11. The faces of the Cherubims in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple looked one towards another, which ſome think ſignified the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement that ſhould be amongſt Miniſters of the Goſpel. So the ſix branches in the Candleſtick joyned all in one; thoſe who hold the light of truth before others, ſhould be united in peace in one, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves. The firſt thing Chriſts Miniſters were to do when they came to any place, was to ſay, <hi>Peace be to that place;</hi> if any ſons of peace were there, they were to abide, otherwiſe not: Surely then it is expected that themſelves ſhould be ſons of peace. The contentions of private Chriſtians are offenſive, but the contentions of Miniſters is a ſcandal with a witneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.21. The great commendation that <hi>Hamor</hi> and <hi>Shechem</hi> give of <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Sons as an argument to perſwade the men of <hi>Shechem</hi> to joyn with them in the giving their Daughters to them for Wives, and in taking theirs, is, <hi>Theſe men are peaceable with us.</hi> A peaceable diſpoſition is very convincing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.6. <hi>My dove, my undefiled is but one, ſhe is the only one of her Mother, ſhe is the choice one of her that bare her.</hi> What then follows? <hi>The Daughters ſaw her and bleſſed her, yea the Queens, and the Concubines, and they praiſed her; Who is ſhe that looketh forth as the Morning, fair as the Moon, clear as the Sun, terrible as an army of Banners?</hi> Let the Saints be but one, and then they will appear beautiful and glorious indeed, yea they will be terrible as an Army of Banners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euagrius</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory records an Epiſtle of <hi>Cyrill of Alexandria,</hi> written to <hi>John of Antioch,</hi> upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a Pacificatory Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> unto him, his Spirit was ſo taken with it that it breaks forth thus: <hi>Let the Heavens rejoyce, and let the earth be glad, the mid-wall of rancour is battered down, the boyling choler which bereaved the minds of quietneſſe, is purged from among us, and all the occaſion of diſcord and diſſention is baniſhed away, for our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt hath granted peace unto the Churches under Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Saints enjoyment of the ſweetneſs of love, peace and unity among themſelves, what is it but heaven upon earth? Heaven is above all ſtorms, tempeſts, troubles, the happineſs of it is perfect reſt. We pray that the will of God might be done on earth as it is done in heaven; why may not we have a heaven upon earth? this would ſweeten all our comforts, yea all our afflictions. But the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil envies us this happineſs. Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
